<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Deathes generall proclamation also fine preceptes of vertuous and honest lyfe.</title>
            <author>Leigh, Valentine, fl. 1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2174</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23104106</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23104106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26237</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26237)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1797:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Deathes generall proclamation also fine preceptes of vertuous and honest lyfe.</title>
                  <author>Leigh, Valentine, fl. 1562.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Sutton dwellyng in Pater noster row at the signe of the blacke boy,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>the 8 day of January, anno M.D.LXI [8 Jan. 1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication begins: "To his very friend Master Henry Coddenham gent. Ualentine Leigh wyshesh health and prosperity."</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸.</note>
                  <note>T.p. has woodcut ill.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26237:1"/>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <head>Deathes proclamation</head>
            <p>Lorde gaue a preſcript precept and lawe to man, through the pronoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyng wherof, our maieſty was firſt ordeined, euen at that preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſpake to Adam theſe wordes: Eatyng, thou ſhalt eate of euery free in the garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the tree of knowlege of good &amp; euyll, thou ſhalt not eate of it: els in what daye thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely dye the death. &amp;c. And thus beyng conceiued, our ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie remained, not long vnborne, and brought foorth, for the ſerpent oure mother (hauyng once deceued the woman, and the woman her huſbande was foorthwith deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to vs, leauynge to vs, as of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, a perpetuall ſtyng, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animate and deuoure the naturall lyfe of all earthly thynges, and ſo we continued, but as yet vnperfect
<pb facs="tcp:26237:1"/> the ſpace of two hundreth &amp; twenty yeares, vntyll wicked Kaym, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled vs to exerciſe and ratify our firſt force, and vertue vpon his iuſt and innocente brother, Abell, who through the violence of our deade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtroke, eftſoones, retourned to a clodde of earthe, frome whyche he deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded not long before. And thus haue we declared brefly the ſumme of our higneſſe petegrie.</p>
            <p>Now concernyng our ineuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble myghte, and indignation, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſed ſythens, vppon eche bodye ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng, it would require hundrethes of yeres, to be by vs particularly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cited. But that you mortall menne oure ſubiectes, myghte the better knowe, howe feeble your predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors haue ben to reſiſt our ſtrength wee thynke it good, for oure more honour, to remembre a fewe exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples,
<pb facs="tcp:26237:2"/> in the ſtede of a numbre. And leaſt, ye might auaunt your ſelues to be ſo muche the nobler, bycauſe your fyrſt parent, Adam, was crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted before vs, we beginning at him lette you to witte, that euen he alſo felte the intollerable poynt of this oure thunderbolte. And ſence his dayes, neyther the iuſte, nor the vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iuſte, the good nor the badde, the rightous nor the vnrightous, the faithfull nor the vnfaithefull, the humble nor the prowde, the meeke nor the ſtubborne, the myghty nor the weake: the ſtowt nor the timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: the wyſe nor the foolyſhe: the wyll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nor the ſymple: the hygh nor the ſowe, the greate nor the ſmall, the fayre nor the fowle: the ſwyfte nor the ſlowe, the healthy nor the ſycke. Themperour, nor his peere, the king nor his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelour: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince
<pb facs="tcp:26237:2"/> nor his ſubiect: the byſhop nor his chaplain: the lord nor his yeomen: the nobilitie nor the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons: The queene nor her maydes: The lady nor her handmaydes: the riche nor the poore, are, or euer were able to plucke their heddes out of our vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall yoake and collar. Neyther man nor beaſt, fyſhe nor fowle, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent or woorme, or any thyng els, poſſeſſynge the breathe of lyfe, in this our worldely kyngedome, but they haue or ſhall taſt the deadly &amp; ineuitable ſhot of this our myghty dart, two only excepted, we meane Enoch and Elyas, who thorough the Omnipotents protection, haue eſcaped our hands, to our no ſmall heauyneſſe. Hercules for all his myghte, nor Sampſon, for all his ſtrength, coulde make agaynſt vs no reſiſtence. Hector the woorthy,
<pb facs="tcp:26237:3"/> Creſus the ryche, Cyrus the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, Annibal the laborous, nor am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bicious Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the great, whom the whole earth coulde not ſatiſfie, were vnable by anye meanes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde from our dint. Sara the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre, Lucrece the chaſte, Penelope the vertuous, Helene the bewtiful, nor pleaſaunte Lais, coulde moue, perſwade, or entice our ſeueritie, to ſpare them any one howre longar, then we had determined. Our ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtye paſſeth not on pleaſures, we regarde not rycheſſe, wee ſet not by iewels: we eſteeme nothyng preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe: we feare not any thretnyngs, wee moue not for manaces, wee ſpare not for pytye: wee relente not wyth mercye, we yelde to no ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw: no dolour troubleth vs nor facte repenteth vs: but as kynge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all, wee vſe oure prerogatiue
<pb facs="tcp:26237:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> withoute controllment: althoughe we confeſſe the ſame oure preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue was vppon Ezechias for .xv. yeares by gods mercye reſtrayned, and his life prolonged. We are that dreadefull deathe, a prince of ſuche maieſtye and notable power, that at oure pleaſure wee doo reape and cutte downe euery creature, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute any exception. We obſerue no tyme, no manners, nor yeares, no lawes, nor no rightes can wyth vs beare ſway: No region no ylande, no natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no people, neither Indes nor Arabies, nor yet thantipodies, are free from our ſubiection. When it is our wyll and pleaſure, our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ſpareth not the pope for his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes, the Emperour for his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, the Kyng for his highnes, the Prince for his auctority, the biſhop for his cleargy, the maieſtrates for
<pb facs="tcp:26237:4"/> their offices: the monkes for theyr cloyſter: the prieſtes, for their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: the Iudge for his iuſtice: the lawyer for his pleadyng: the catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poll for his mace: the landlorde for his rentes, the merchaunte for his rycheſſe: the farmor for his goods: the graſier for his cattal: the poore for their pouertie: the mayſter for his preeminence: the ſeruaunt for his diligence: the freeman for his libertie: nor the priſoner or captiue for his bondes anguiſhe or diſtres. Whoſoeuer ouercommeth, who ſo euer vanquiſſheth: who ſo euer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerrunnethe: who ſo euer brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth down: whoſoeuer deſtroyeth, who ſo euer by fortune or manhod atchieueth to the hyghe chayre of honour, yet doo what he can, in the ſpite of his beard, we wil haue the laſt victorye. The yonge luſty gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant
<pb facs="tcp:26237:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> flouriſhyng in the beſte prime of his yeares healthy or wealthy, ſubſtanciall and ryche, beautyfull &amp; amorous, flowyng in pleaſures, araied with natures lineamentes, and ſwymmynge in all earthly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions, we can intumulate and incloaſe in a moment, within a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſepulchre, where his deade car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas ſhall remayne, to be deuoured by woormes, and his ſowle tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to an vnknowen place. No walle, no tower, no bullwarke, no dyche, no doore, no locke, no force, or fortreſſe, no dungeon, deapth or defence, canne kepe vs out, but our maieſtye wyll vſe our ineſtymable power ouer al men, in euery place. Neither haue we reſpect of nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or ignobilitie, of youth, or of age: but as ſoone take we the chylde, as the aged, the babe vnborne, as the
<pb facs="tcp:26237:5"/> ancient horehead: the ſtrong as the impotent: for we doo accompt oure highnes, and ſo in dede we are lord wholly of the temporall world, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouryng all lyuyng creatures, like as our brother Tyme waſteth and conſumeth in proceſſe of yeares, all other earthly thyngs. Our maieſty ſmileth in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceite many tymes when we call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, what innumerable people, the tyrannye of kynges, the crueltye of prynces, the extremitye of maieſtrates, the parcialitie of officers, wyth the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the lawes haue ſente here before, &amp; dayly do ſend to our man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and dwellyng place, yea euery one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> either warres or the ſworde dooth confound, fyre conſume, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters drowne or ouerflowe, famyne deuoure, ſycknes exhauſt, age take away, or time doth bury: they al we
<pb facs="tcp:26237:5"/> ſaye, lande at our hauen, to vs they come, one tyme or an other. We ar that onely porte, wherat, wyl they, or nyll they, they muſte ones make their arriuall. And of thys thynge, aboue al other our highnes is moſt able to boſte, that our maieſtie ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thither, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s thei neuer or ſeldom, make their return, to tell any tales agayne. And that you oure ſubiectes maye the better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that we are no leſſe, but a myghty &amp; terrible prynce, the ſame doth and may euidently appere by our ſeruants &amp; miniſters, whyche ar almoſt inexpugnable, as peryls and daungers, quarels, malicious conſpiracies, battayles, murders, poyſons, ruines ſyckneſſes, edge-tooles, gunnes, gynnes, ſnares, deceytes, and innumerable other ſuche lyke, of all ſortes, by the
<pb facs="tcp:26237:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26237:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26237:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26237:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26237:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> whiche men do ſuffre eyther hurt perdition or other damage. What man is there liuyng vnder the ſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, that would not hartyly laugh if he were but a while in our place or throne, to ſee bothe kynges and maieſtrates vpon lyght diſpleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or for ſmall offences, violently to force our cruell ſtyng, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the liues of their ſeruantes or ſubiectes, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they them ſelues cannot obteyne at oure handes, for their owne lyues, any ſure patente for ſo lyttle tyme, as halfe an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers ſpace: Yea and oure maieſtie ofte tymes for oure pleaſure, dooth not ſuffre them to lyue many minu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, after the bitter &amp; heauy deathe of their ſaid ſely vnderlynges. And in this one point alſo, our highnes hygh preminence muche ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth all the reſt: that although oure
<pb facs="tcp:26237:8"/> fatall vigour is common ouer all men, yet the daye and tyme of our comming and approch is ſo vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, that euery one except a fewe in numbre) as Moſes, Aaron, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias, Symeon. &amp;c. or euer they bee aware of vs, or yet do loke for our commyng, are dayly with our mace ſodeynly areſted and entrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. It is a wonder to ſee howe all people leade their lyfe without any reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of our maieſty: &amp; more meruayl to behold their greedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of worldly thynges: From the fruition wherof, we take theim vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly away or euer thei can or haue throughly enioyed any ſmal part or portion of the ſame. Where the am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bitious dothe continually gape ſo for honor &amp; promotion, as though they were immortall, our maieſtie vntwineth the threde of his life in
<pb facs="tcp:26237:9"/> leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the twinalyng of an eie by reaſon wherof, foorthwith his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour fleeth away, &amp; nothyng there remaineth but a vile clod of donge and clay. Who ſeeth not the proude man, ſo deſpiſyng al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though he ſhuld ſhortly be exalted into the third heauens, where we, in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ouerthrowe his great glory, ſende hym to Lucyfer, his greate graund maſter, in the depth of the helles? Who noteth not, the leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and glutton, ſo pamperynge his bealye, and ſeekyng to ſatisfye his luſtes, as though he wer a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morant inſatiable: where we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes ſende hym ſodaynely on meſſage to our brother Pluto, to ſuffre woorthyly with hym moſte terrible paynes. Ye ſee manyfeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the ryche and the couetous, ſo ſcrapynge, and hoordynge, the
<pb facs="tcp:26237:9"/> worldes wicked mucke, as though they wente aboute, here to ſtabliſhe their dwellyng endleſſe: Where we in a ſodeyne, leaue their dead car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſes to wormes: &amp; yelde ouer their ſowles to be perpetually tourmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with horrible deuyls. And for the moſt parte, we do ſteale vpon al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at ſuch vnſet ſteue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or vnware times, as we do apprehend ſom ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge, ſome drynkynge, ſome ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, ſome dancyng, ſome ſingyng, ſome wepyng, ſome ſorowyng, ſom laughyng, ſome wowyng, ſom ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryeng, ſome bargaynyng, ſome by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng, ſome ſelling, ſome trauailyng, ſome reſtynge, ſome rydyng, ſome ſaylyng, ſome huntyng, ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, ſomme teachynge, ſomme defrawdynge, ſome pollynge, ſome buyldynge, ſome ouerthrowynge, ſomme catchynge, ſome ſpendyng,
<pb facs="tcp:26237:10"/> ſome at noone days, ſome at night, ſome in the mornyng, and ſome in the euenyng, and ſom at mydnyght It is a worlde to beholde, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate our commynge is to all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, except it be to a very fewe: we meane ſuch, as ar either ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with great cares, ſorowes, gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous tormentes and extreme pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or els to ſuche as remayne in execrable captiuitie, ſeruitude, or bondage: To all other ſortes, we are as welcome as water into the ſhyppe. Lord what a reuell and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance we make, where as wee come once in place. If our maieſtie take our progreſſe to the noble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maieſtrate, or welthy rich man, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye ye ſee verified the ſayenge of Syrake, whyche ſayth: Oh Death howe bitter is the remembrance of thee, to a man that ſeketh reſt and
<pb facs="tcp:26237:10"/> comfort in his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and riches? for he is ſo vnprouided for our com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynge, what wyth the loue of the worlde, the loue of hys rycheſſe, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, &amp; poſſeſſions, the loue or affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to hys deare wyfe, chyldren, howſes, gardens, and pleaſures: &amp; what with the heauye trouble and woorme of conſcience: the bitter re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of hys former lyfe euilly ſpent: the recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and reſtoryng of euyl gotten goodes: beſides that his extreme feare, painfull ſicknes, and anguyſſhe: that yf the mooſte mercyfulle grace of the Father al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myghtye, bee not preſente, hee ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth Diſpayre for hys chiefeſte re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuge: and in the tyme of thys hys paſſyng, (through oure arreſt) hys wyfe crieth out, hys children wepe, his ſeruantes bewayle, &amp; hys fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des lamente: that there appeareth
<pb facs="tcp:26237:11"/> nothynge but ſorowe and heuynes on euerye ſyde. Further, his eyes by vs once ſhut and cloaſed, there is by and by no ſmalle adooe and ruffle in his houſe, his children wil to law for their patrimonie, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutours for his goodes, his wife for her porcion and dowry: the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes for their parte, wyth ſuche thunderynge threatnynges, cruell wordes and countenaunces one to an other eche bodye pylferyng and patching, ſcambling and ſnatching ſtealynge and catchynge, as oure hyghnes beleueth that in our ſayd Brother Plutos kyngdome, there is not the like tragedies. After like manner, when our maieſtie repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to the cotage of the poore man or needye, foorthwith he is no leſſe vexed, callyng to mynde his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde and moſte heynous offences,
<pb facs="tcp:26237:11"/> the doubtful place and vnknowen Iudge, whether and before whom he muſt preſently go, to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for al his crimes, curſes, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and vnpaciencie, with other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll deedes by him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, in the tyme of his lyfe. Beſydes this, to leaue his poore wyfe, and children fatherleſſe, in penury and comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, is no ſmall corſey to his poore harte in that laſte hower: they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentyng, cryeng, and moſte bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly curſyng our hyghnes for ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reauynge theim of their chiefe and onely defence of poore lyuynge.</p>
            <p>Thus where ſoeuer our maieſty is, or abydeth, there is nothing els hearde nor ſeene but deepe ſyghes, loude ſcrikyngs, wofull wringyng of handes, and heauy ſalte teares: For we are named to bee Lorde of lamentation, kyng of all ſorowes,
<pb facs="tcp:26237:12"/> gouerner of miſeries, &amp; the ground of all kynd of greuous calamities, yea, what infelicitye is there wyth tongue, to be ſpoken or harte to bee thought, but oure maieſtie ſomety<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes put them in vre and exerciſe?</p>
            <p>If our highnes come ones to a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flict or battaile, as we are neuer ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent, we do warant you, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, though there were a hundreth of theym, in ſundrye places, at one mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of time, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forthwith there maye men ſee of all ſortes of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and miſchiefes heapes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundaunce. Some are ſente to vs fightyng, ſome fleeyng, ſome aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, ſome yeldyng: ſome come to vs headleſſe ſomme ouerthrowne, ſome clouen to the teeth, ſom thruſt through the hart, ſom riuen in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by gunſhot, ſom ſtriken down, ſome troden vnder foote, ſome ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyng
<pb facs="tcp:26237:12"/> for breath: ſome moſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly yellyng and gronyng. So that by theyr moſte hydeous cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, dolorous ſyghynges, and dredefull ſhowtes, it is ryghte wel knowen, ſene, and perceyued, and they throughly feele, that our ſayd highnes is amongeſt theim, as a bloude thirſtye god, to receaue the bloudy ſacrifices of their woful ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. And thus from tyme to tyme, hath thinexplicable power &amp; might of our maieſtie flouriſhed ſens the fyrſt killyng of iuſte Abell, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and ſhall ſo continue, vntyll the vtter conſummation of heuen and erth by fyre. For theſe therfore and ſundry other conſiderations, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth all you oure ſubiectes, of force and neceſſitie, to feare our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; diſpleſure.</p>
            <p>Nowe alſo we wyl let you part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:26237:13"/> to vnderſtande with what ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie we doo miniſter our iuſtice: for ſeeyng that true equitie and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice conſiſteth in equall indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be diſtributed to al men alike without any fauor or reſpect, then dare and may our maieſtie boldely challenge, that there is none iuſter thenne wee. For who can, or euer could reproue vs of parcialitie, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng we execute our force as wel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the prince as the abiect, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ryche, as the poore, extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhynge the lyfe of eche lyuynge creature, vnder one our law, order or decree &amp; firſt conſtitution. If gif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes coulde haue bribed vs, poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue ſatisfied vs, requeſtes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome vs, or pleſures haue wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs, then are we aſſured, we ſhould ſhortely haue proued the welthieſt the rycheſte and the happyeſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:26237:13"/> the ſonne. But oure hyghneſſe neuer ſpared any that euer remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the compaſſe of our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynion or iuriſdiction, ſence the worldes fyrſte creation, hethervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, No not that Innocente and myghty prince, <hi>IESVS,</hi> the deere beeloued ſonne and heyre of oure omnipotente Father: but euen hee alſo felte and ſuſteyned the myght of our violence, through the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dyligence of Satans truſtye myniſters, the wicked Iewes.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we partely aduertiſed all you mortall creatures, our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terrour of our inuincible puiſſance, and the righteous ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of oure Iuſtyce. And nowe ſhall wee brefely ſignifie vnto you what innumerable benefyttes all perſonnes, of eche eſtate condition and degree, doo dayly receaue by
<pb facs="tcp:26237:14"/> oure auctoritie. And fyrſte, for thobſeruyng of order, we wyll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with you Emperors and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes, you Kyngs and Quenes, you princes and princeſſes, and all ſuche, ſuperiour maieſtrates, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge our chiefe and principall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes: If our power were not, wee ſaie, ye, of all other ſhoulde lyue in moſte cares and fearefulnes. For we of our cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, take away your traitours, proſtrate your enemies, ridde you of your rebelles, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhe your aduerſaries, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng your bodies to ſuertie, youre realmes to tranquillitie, your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to peace, and abundance of all thynges: where as if the vigour of our maieſtie were not, they would abandon you from your ſceptures and diademes, bereaue you of your eſtates: caſt you into moſt greuous
<pb facs="tcp:26237:14"/> thraldom and miſeries. Alſo what gracious good tournes doo all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welthes, and al ſortes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſuſtein by our fauorable frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp and magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? Which way coulde the landlorde enioy his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, rents and poſſeſſions: the mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chant his goodes and his merchan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſe: the huſbandeman his corne &amp; his cattall: the crafteſman the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of his facultie and ſcience: the labourer his hyre or his wages, if our power were not? What matro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnrauiſhed, what wyues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, what maides &amp; virgins vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>defloured ſhould there be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole erth, if we were not a rightous reward to thoffenders: What wealthy men ſpoyled, what good men wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, what pooremen oppreſſed, what wicked men exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abiected, what
<pb facs="tcp:26237:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> trauaylours murthered: what iuſt men betraied, what officers kylled and reſyſted ſhould there be, yf we were not a terrible ſcourge to the wicked? What religion, what lawe what equitie, what fayth, what iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, what truth, what innocency, what Chaſtytie, what wedlocke, what honeſtie, what Obedyence, ſhoulde bee founde or ſeene in any place, if we were not the goulf that ſwallowe all tranſgreſſours? Nay, what wronge, what iniurye, what diſobedience, what manſlaughter, what theft, what treaſon, what con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpyracyes, what lyinge in wayte, what bloudſhede, what oppreſſion, what extorcion, what rape, what inceſte, what fornication, what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterie, what witchecraft, what ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceries, what hereſies, blaſphemies and mooſte deteſtable Iniquityes
<pb facs="tcp:26237:15"/> woulde abounde and ouerflowe in euery place, if our grace were not the rooter out of malefactours.</p>
            <p>No countrey, no realm, no citie, no towne, no village, no hamlet, nor any mans habitation coulde ſtand or continue any tyme vncorrupted defaced, or vtterlye deſtroyed, yf it were not oure pleaſure to ſhorten the lyues of euill and wycked men, and to cutte of the pernicious, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitefull, and rotten membres of all inhabited regyons. Throughe the bountyfulle and beneuolente goodnes of our maieſtie, Religion is eſtablyſhed in his due honoure and reuerence: the Gouernours o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed in the myniſtration of theyr lawes: the godly are cheryſhed: the meke are ſupported: thoſe that are vertuous are eſtemed: the iuſte are preferred: the honeſt commended:
<pb facs="tcp:26237:16"/> and al publike good ordres and ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutes conſerued. Who can then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the premiſſes duely wayed, but that our highnes inuincible power is to all mortall men, a thyng moſt neceſſary: as without the whiche, the whole earth wold in ſhort tyme hee ſo repleniſhed with iniquitie, that euen hel it ſelf (as we thinke) would be the better of the twayne. Moreouer, this inconuenience we coniect would haue ben, and come to paſſe, yf wee had ſuffred all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and people to haue remained ſtyl on line, frome the beginnyng of the worlde, vntill this preſent day: that tenne ſuche earthes as this is: would not haue ſuffiſed to haue fed and preſerued theym with neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuſtenaunce. And nowe for the declaration of our ſundry other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, who ſeeth not, how the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb facs="tcp:26237:16"/> our maieſtie dooth approche to the faithefull, the hartlier they doe reioyce: and when wee come, they imbrace vs cherefully: to the poore &amp; oppreſſed our preſence is ioyous: to the captiue confortable: to the tormented, happy: to the pacient in his extremitie of ſyckneſſe, wyſhed for: and to innumerable others ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry acceptable. And that our ſubiect Iob ryght well knewe, whenne he cried: Wherfore is the lyght gyuen to hym that is in miſerye, and lyfe vnto them that haue heuy hartes, which longe for death: and though it come not, woulde digge it out of high places, which alſo woulde be excedynge glad and reioyce, if they could fynd theyr graue any where. Yea and our ſubiect Syrak repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no leſſe of our maieſtie, ſaying Oh Deathe, howe acceptable and
<pb facs="tcp:26237:17"/> good is your iudgemente vnto the nedefull, &amp; to hym whoſe ſtrength fayleth, or that is nowe in his laſte age, or that is full of care or feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, vnto him alſo that is in de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpaire, or that hath no hope or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience? Thus you ſee well howe the commynge of our hyghnes is gratefull to an infinite multitude. Furthermore, ſens that now it eui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dently appereth, the whole worlde to be almoſt drowned in filthines, and ſhamleſſe maners, flowyng in deceates, and ſurmountyng in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: where neither faithe, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, peace, iuſtice, reſt, or quietneſſe remaineth. Where mooſte horrible crimes rule ouer al: where the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intendeth the bane of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: where the ſonne oft thirſteth tyll we fetche his father: where the
<pb facs="tcp:26237:17"/> woman ofte longeth tyll we ſtrike her huſbande: where the man as muche hungreth tyl we catche his wyfe: wheremoſte men ſcrapeth, coueteth and hourdeth: where eche man ſpeaketh fayre, and woorketh the contrary: where chaſtitie is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, and matrimonie polluted: where hunger, thyrſte, ſicknes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie, nedynes, nakedneſſe, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, impriſonment, and ſo many daungers and continuall labours doo aſſayle men on al ſydes: where all kynde of miſeries doo ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe all maner of creatures, that none or veraie fewe in numbre, in all their lyues, can lyue one whole daie out of ſome vexation or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Nowe what wyſe manne is there then that ſettyng apart al af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and ryghtely ponderynge the manifolde cares, perils, grefes,
<pb facs="tcp:26237:18"/> and ſorowes wherwith mans lyfe is enuironned on euery ſyde, dothe not worthelye iudge our maieſtyes commynge, to be daily wiſſhed for: yea, and thoſe creatures to be three tymes bleſſed, that ſooneſt aryueth at our ſure landing place. Such is the beneuolence of oure hyghneſſe, that we fynyſhe al paines, we looſe all bondes, we dryue awaye feare, and exclude all doubtes. Yea, and lyke as men before (their concepti-and natiuitie) knew no lack, no he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, no penurie, no oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no diſtreſſe, vnquietnes or trouble: no more ſhal the good fele any the like beyng once paſſed our narowe and ſtrayte paſſage. And as our maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie ſuppoſeth in our conceite, who ſo hath once eſcaped the terrour of our violence, he ſtandeth by and by ſafe on the ſhoare, and derydynge
<pb facs="tcp:26237:18"/> lawghyng at the foly of others his ſucceſſours, whyche had rather be ſtyll tombled and toſſed with the ſtormy tempeſt is and horrible ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in the cruel &amp; troubleſom ſeas of worldly miſeries, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to prepare themſelues redily to paſſe through vs into quietnes. Thus haue we ſufficientely opened &amp; proued to all you our louyng ſubiectes, the force of our highneſſe, the iuſtice of our maieſtie, &amp; the beneuolent clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of our gracious goodneſſe, that (regardynge youre moſte bounden dueties of allegeance) ye might the rather in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration therof, feare and obey vs, worthily eſteeme vs, and humblye thanke vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FINALLY</hi> foraſmuche as oure maieſtie doth wel ponder and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue our owne highneſſe (in this latter age of the worlde) which dra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth
<pb facs="tcp:26237:19"/> faſte to his appoynted ende and conſummation, to be wel nere growne to the latter tyme of oure yeares: and conſyderyng alſo that our myght, force, and violence (by reaſon of our ſhorte continuaunce hereafter, is nowe farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme to all people, then it was at the begynnyng, when Adam, as ye reade, lyued .viii. hundreth yeares. Noe .ix. hundreth and .xv. yeares, and Abraham Clxxv. yeres, where as we doo not ſuffre you oure ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes nowe adaies ye ſe, and moſt of this tyme, to lyue paſſyng fiftye or .lx. yeres, or at the vttermoſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpityng very fewe tyl they may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of .lxx. or ful .lxxx.</p>
            <p>Further, for that we throughely perceiue, that ſens our fyrſt creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the fall of man, when he was ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed out of that pleaſant garden
<pb facs="tcp:26237:19"/> of Edom, there was neuer age of all the ſixe ages paſt, that euer did flowe or abounde in ail kynde of iniquitye and abhomination, as this laſte age dooth, whiche walo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth all togither in ſinne and wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes, and is growen to ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chief, that if it ſhould long endure, men wold ſcant beleue, there were either God, heauen, or helle, after this mortall lyfe: but that by oure ſeparation of the lyfe from the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kas, both body &amp; ſoule wer vtterly extincte: yea and all hope of reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection fruſtrat. We therfore of our maieſties mere motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpecial grace and beneuolence, wiſhyng the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of all, and the diſtruction of none, if it might be, do preſently pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bliſh and declare vnto you, &amp; euery of you, our louing ſubiects, throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghout our hole earthly dominions
<pb facs="tcp:26237:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> this our general pleaſure, precept, and laſte commaundement (beyng the only ground, waightieſt cauſe, and pithyeſt matter, ment, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and expreſſed in this our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation) that we in the name of our owne Supreme maieſtie and hyghneſſe, doo generally wyll and requyre you, and neuertheleſſe in the behalfe of the father omnypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente, oure eternall ſoueraigne doo ſtraightly charge, and commaunde you, and euery of you, of what ſexe, age, ſtate, degree, or condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ye be, or herafter ſhalbe, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlye vpon the recept, ſyght, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng, notice or publication of theſe preſentes all delayes and excuſes ſette aparte, wyth aſmuche conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyente ſpeede and dylygence as is poſſyble, euery one of you, prepare youre ſelues wyllyngely to leaue
<pb facs="tcp:26237:20"/> thys vayne worlde, and to forgoe the vanities, inticementes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaptefull pleaſures of thys frayle and tranſytorye lyte, makynge you redye and meete, to attende and wayte on our maieſtyes perſonne, where and whenne ſo euer ye ſhall by our auctorytye be ſodeinly ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned, cyted, or called: that at our vnknowen commyng: ye may be thoroughe oure hygheneſſe areſte founde gladde, and preſte to paſſe into an other muche better lyfe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenyſhed wyth al ſtable ioyes and tranquyllytye. Further, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge all you oure louynge ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the meane tyme, to fall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce for youre former euyll lyues, to crye hartelye to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtye, to graunte you hys mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, to Sacryfyce to hym youre humble prayers, euen frome the
<pb facs="tcp:26237:21"/> bottome of your ſorye and contrite heartes: to obeye his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: to ſeeke onely his prayſe and honour in all your deedes: to relieue your poore brethren with parte of your goodes: And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, to lyue chriſtianly, to deale iuſtly, and to paſſe youre tyme ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſely, that beeynge once paſſed vs, ye may enter into the glorious kyngedome of God the Fathers dere ſonne, and our halfe brother, Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Fayle ye not this to dooe, as ye entende, not onely to auoyde ours but alſo his terrible indignation for dooynge the contrarye, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo incurre in the latter dreadefulle daye, the heauye bitter, and mooſte wofull domynyon of oure cruelle Succeſſoure, Deathe eternall.</p>
            <p>Where, we aſſure you, remayneth
<pb facs="tcp:26237:21"/> nothynge, but moſte horrible pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, inexplicable tormentes, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſorowes, endleſſe diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ineffable terrour, and gnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng of teeth, with fyre and brym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtone perpetually bournynge, and durable for euer.</p>
            <p>¶Geuen at our maieſties inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble honour and pallaice imperiall, Situate in the Ayrie Region, the laſte day of Iune, in the yeare ſince our highnes firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, accordyng to the wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng of the Hebrues, fyue thouſande .v. hundred, and eyghtene.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="precepts">
            <pb facs="tcp:26237:22"/>
            <head>Here folovveth fyue precep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of pure and honeſt lyfe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſte, To feare, prayſe, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Almyghty God, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Creatoure of heauen and earthe, and all thynges therein conteyned, with an humble and faithfull mynde, that is not defiled or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taminated with fleſhely luſte, worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires or wicked affections, is the chief and moſte principall poynt of perfect vertue or vnſpotted lyfe.</p>
            <p>The nexte and ſeconde is, That a man warely take hede to his talke, ſpeeche, or tonge: That he neuer ſpeake eyther blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemye of God, ſlaunder of his neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or any wicked lyes, or vntruth.</p>
            <p>And for his better inſtruction, let manne haue alwayes theſe three tymes apointed for communication in his remembrance: Not to ſpeake but when a queſtion is aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked of hym, or when no neceſſitie conſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth hym to demaunde a queſtion: or to enforme or enſtructe any parſon in know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge, vertue, or honeſt maners to the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties edification, to whome he ſpeaketh. In theſe three only preſcribed tymes, Speche
<pb facs="tcp:26237:22"/> is better then ſylence: In all other tymes it is better to holde a mans tongue then to ſpeake, for ſylence is the handmayde to wyſedome and prudence.</p>
            <p>The third rule or precept is, To be low<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and gentyll of behauiour and maners, that is, To ſalute euery man gladlye, to preſume before none, to contemne or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe no perſone (be their eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neuer ſo meane, poore, or ſymple)</p>
            <p>And this rule is ſo profytable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſocietie of mans lyfe, that it wil not only procure, and continue a good name to him, who ſo vſeth it, but alſo to brynge to paſſe, that he ſhall haue eche man to bee his frende, and none to be his ennemy.</p>
            <p>The fowerth rule to bee learned is, To abandon and vtterly eſchewe all bodylye luſte, vayne pleaſures, play, and ydlenes, the nouriſher of vices. And to forſee, that thoſe battes and enticementes be with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancye wholly abiected &amp; repulſed. For who ſeeth not in fleſhely luſt and delytes, three continuall euyls, that is to ſay, The exhauſtynge or conſumynge of the lyuely vygour and powers, as well of the body, as of the mynde: The haſtenynge alſo of
<pb facs="tcp:26237:23"/> ryueled age, with the ſhortnyng of mans lyfe. And the heauye and moſte wofull bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge or gnawynge of that helly ſcorpion repentaunce. Now in pleaſures and play what is there followinge, but extreme fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, waſte and loſſe of that precious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure Tyme, and in the ende (for the moſte parte) myſerye, pouertye, and diſpayre.</p>
            <p>And as for ydleneſſe, is not onelye of all theſe euylles aboue reherſed, but alſo of a thouſande miſchiefes moe, the very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone, ladye, and mayſtreſſe, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye patheway to Pluto his infernal dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng place.</p>
            <p>The fyfthe rule or poynt to be learned, is, Daiely with dilygence and attencion to applye thy ſelfe to ſome vertuouſe and godly exerciſe, that is to ſay: Thou muſte addicte thy mynde to the ſtudye and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of ſome ſerious and lawdable ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,, or knowledge, whiche maye eyther preſently be a lanterne to thy lyfe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, or nowe and hereafter profitable to the mayntenance and lawfull honeſte augmentation of thy lyuynge and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce: lettynge no daye eſcape with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute dooyng ſomme beneficiall exercyſe, that at the viſitation of ſyckeneſſe or age,
<pb facs="tcp:26237:23"/> thou bee not oppreſſed with myſerye and indigence, for the lacke of humayne neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, whyche wyll then ouerwhealme thee with intollerable calamities.</p>
            <trailer>¶Thus endeth theſe fyue preceptes of vertuous and honeſt lyfe, wourthye to bee mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked, and folowed.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="approbation">
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Peruſed and allovved according to the Quenes maieſties iniunctions.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26237:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Henry Sutton dwellyng in Pater noſter row at the ſigne of the blacke Boy.</head>
            <p>The .8. day of Ianuary. <hi>Anno. M.D.LXI.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26237:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26237:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26237:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26237:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
